Okay, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is the last דף daf of
מסכת יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, קכ"ב, Kof Chaf Bet, 122. We pick up
three lines from the bottom on קכ"א עמוד ב' Kof Chaf Alef
Amud Bet and we are dealing with the question about who is
believed to testify that a man has died. And the משנה mishnah
introduced the issue about women, children; women we had already implicitly had
before,
but also even things that seem to be like just conversational, not
intentional,
said in passing, and by the non-Jew maybe specifically if it was
said only in passing, מסיח לפי תומו, mesiach lefi tumo, otherwise there's
a concern that maybe it's intentionally being a misrepresentation in order to
cause problems. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up three lines on
the bottom.
So where were we? ההוא עובד כוכבים... Hahu oveid kochavim... Oh, we
also had the important point at the end yesterday that was
that even though in a case of מים שאין להם סוף mayim
she'ein lahem sof a woman is not allowed to remarry, nevertheless, if
she does go ahead and remarry, then in one case even without
a פסק, psak, we do not make her divorce. So that was
also a very important leniency. And as Rabbi Dov pointed out at
the end of yesterday, which we failed to mention, there was obviously
a little pun going on because the guy who had drowned, his
name was חסא, Chasa, which is lettuce, and the statement of רב
נחמן Rav Nachman was that the fish are eating חסא, Chasa, are
eating the lettuce,
on the basis of which the wife went and remarried assuming that
it was a פסק psak or a that the husband had died.
Okay, anyway we pick up now three lines from the bottom. ההוא
עובד כוכבים דהוה קאמר ליה לישראל, Hahu oveid kochavim de-hava ka amar
lei le-Yisrael,
so there was a certain non-Jew that told the Jew, טול אספסתא
ושדי לחיותא בשבתא, tol aspasta u-shadi le-cheivata be-Shabta, you know, cut down
this fodder or
you know this grain, the חספא chaspa is like the stuff that
does not yet have grain on it, fodder I guess, and throw
it to my animals on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so he was forcing
a Jew to work for him on שבת Shabbat and to cut
this grain. ואי לא קטלינא לך כדקטלינא לפלוני בר ישראל, Ve-i lo
katlina lach kide-katlina le-Ploni bar Yisrael,
and if you don't do it, I will kill you like I
killed this other Jew, ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, דאמרי ליה,
de-amri lei, I said to him, בשלי לי קדירה בשבתא, bashili li
kederah be-Shabta,
cook for me a pot on שבת, Shabbat, ולא בשיל לי, ve-lo
bashil li, and he refused to cook for me on שבת, Shabbat,
וקטלתיה, ve-kataltiyeh, and I killed him. So you better you better do
this stuff for me on שבת Shabbat or else I'll kill you
like I killed this other Jew who wouldn't do work for me
on שבת. Shabbat. שמעת דביתהו, Shama'at deveiteihu,
so the wife heard of the guy who he said he had
killed and who apparently hadn't been home for a while and she
was wondering what had happened to him. So the wife heard about
this ואתאי לקמיה דאביי ve-atai lekamei de-Abaye and came to אביי. Abaye.
So it says you know what's the story? So this non-Jew said
it sounds like a little מסיח לפי תומו, mesiach lefi tumo, right?
Which from our משנה mishnah is okay, he's not doing to testify,
he's just sort of taking it as a point like he's assuming
it as a fact and just happening to mention it. So can
I assume my husband is dead? שהשהה שלשה רגלים, She-hishah shelosha regalim,
he made her wait three רגלים. regalim. Why?
So obviously he was conflicted about what the הלכה halacha was here.
Now רש"י Rashi says either because at the רגלים regalim that's when,
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, שהיו תלמידי חכמים נקבצים לשמוע הדרשה
הלכות פסח בפסח. she-hayu talmidei chachamim nikbatzin lishmoa ha-derashah hilchot Pesach be-Pesach.
So one is as we know that that there would be a
big gathering at time of the רגלים regalim to be learning the
הלכות halachot of the חג chag and so he was going to
ask you know he was going to ask his colleague at that
time for their opinion about this. Right? Well I don't know, so
maybe he wasn't he didn't find he asked all three you know
he kept on asking and he didn't feel that he got a
good resolution. Now then רש"י Rashi has
another interesting answer, בתשובת הגאונים מצאתי כל הני רגלי דאמוראי היינו יום
שמת
בו אדם גדול,
bi-teshuvat ha-Geonim matzati kol hanei reglei
de-Amora'ei hainu yom she-met bo adam gadol, a רגל regel
here does not mean the רגלים regalim like the pilgrimage holidays. It
means period of time.
He waited three, sorry, three years.
Right. So here there is three יארצייט. yahrtzeit. Right. So here the
גאונים Geonim read this practice of יארצייט yahrtzeit into this גמרא, Gemara,
right? Because we you know we have no early we have no
real reference in the גמרא Gemara to an idea of you know
of יארצייט. yahrtzeit.
But רש"י Rashi
says by the גאונים Geonim apparently רגלי דאמוראי היינו יום שמת בו
אדם גדול, reglei de-Amora'ei hainu yom she-met bo adam gadol,
so they didn't say by anybody but like by a major sage,
קובעים אותו לכבודו, kov'im oto lichvodo, you
you commemorate the day of death the anniversary of death, ומדי שנה
בשנה כשמגיע אותו היום מתקבצים תלמידי חכמים מכל סביביו, u-midei shanah be-shanah
keshe-magia oto hayom mitkabtzin talmidei chachamim mikol sevivav, all the sages gather
from in the area, ובאים על
קברו עם שאר עם להושיב ישיבה שם u-ba'im al kivro im shear
am le-hoshiv yeshivah sham
and they have a day of learning in commemoration of the person's
death. So here you have an idea of like a יארצייט yahrtzeit
lecture and a special day of a יארצייט yahrtzeit specifically for a
big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So again it's obviously being read into
the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara isn't saying any of this, but
it's fascinating to see that that was already something that's a practice
of
the
גאונים. Geonim. anyway so he waited these three periods to get input
from other sages and still wasn't able to resolve the question for
her. So אמר לה רב אדא בר אהבה amar lah Rav Adda
bar Ahava so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava said
to her, because she's maybe getting frustrated, so she's asking some other
opinions, זיל לקמיה דרב יוסף. zil l'kamei d'Rav Yosef. You know what,
you should go ask רב יוסף Rav Yosef who was אביי's Abaye's
רבי, rebbi, דחריף סכינא. deharif sakhina.
He's got a sharp knife. Okay, he can help you split the
hairs that you have to... he can help you like he'll be
able to resolve this issue for her. אזלה לקמיה, azla l'kamei, so
he went to she went to him. פשט מהא, pashat meha, he's
included her status from the following from the following ברייתא. braita. It
says מהא מתניתין meha masnisan or it should be מתניתא. masnisa. עובד
כוכבים oved kokhavim who was selling פירות בשוק, peiros bashuk, a non-Jew
was selling fruit in the marketplace, ואמר פירות הללו של ערלה הן,
v'amar peiros halalu shel orla hen, these fruit are really great, they're
from a tree that's only been you know that's only borne you
know started to bear fruit, it's only in its second year since
it's been planted. So he didn't explicitly say they're אסור assur and
they're ערלה, orla, but he was saying that they are from a
second year tree let's say. של עזקה הן. shel azaka hen. They
are of עזקה. azaka. Now what is עזקה? azaka? So רש״י Rashi
says the explanation רש״י Rashi prefers is עזקה azaka is a place
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and he's selling them in חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz and there's a question of whether you have to worry
about their being טבל tevel not taken תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. The
other read of עזקה azaka that רש״י Rashi didn't like is he
says that they're fruit that has been in a field that was
guarded on שמיטה. shmita. Okay,
as to the verb meaning like to guard or to protect. The
reason רש״י Rashi doesn't like it is because all these cases is
the non-Jew is saying something that makes it halachically problematic. And רש״י
Rashi says why does guarding a field on שמיטה shmita make the
fruit forbidden? Either the fruit is מותר mutter before the time of
ביעור biur or it's forbidden after the time of ביעור. biur. What
does that have to do if you watch the fruit on שמיטה?
shmita? And there's a very relevant and important הלכה halacha especially now
that it's the שמיטה shmita year. So if you take a quick
look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says של עזקה, shel azaka, פירש בקונטרס
מפרדס מוזק ומשומר ושביעית היא, perish bekuntrus mipardes muzak u'meshumar u'shvi'it hi,
וקשיא ליה, ve'kashya leh, so
that's they've been a protected field on שמיטה, shmita, but רש״י Rashi
is bothered, אי קודם ביעור לעולם מותר, ei kodem biur l'olam mutter,
and who cares, since when does fruit become אסור? assur? והביא רבנו
תם דבהדיא תניא בתורת כהנים ואת ענבי נזיריך לא תבצור, ve'heivi Rabbeinu
Tam de'hedya tanya be'Toras Kohanim v'es invey nezirecha lo tivtzor, don't harvest
your grapes, מן המשומר אי אתה בוצר, min hamshumar ee atta botzer,
you cannot harvest from grapes that have been protected, like you know
kept the other people out that you've exerted your ownership over them,
אלא אתה בוצר מן המופקר, ela atta botzer min hamufkar, but you
can from stuff that has been allowed to be הפקר. hefker. So
that actually the act of שמירה shmira and of exerting your בעלות,
ba'alus, your ownership over the field, makes it, א, alef, prohibited to
harvest, but presumably possibly also makes the fruit forbidden as well. And
this, again, it's so fascinating that this very central question, right, is
not discussed in a משנה, mishna, it's not discussed in ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
he has to quote the תורת כהנים, Toras Kohanim, רש״י Rashi doesn't
even reference it. So it's quite fascinating how some central laws of
שמיטה, shmita, you know, are are so debated and so much based
on very you know very sparse evidence. So that's just fascinating and
I mention it because it's a שמיטה shmita year. But anyway, back
to the גמרא. Gemara. I don't know why he doesn't mention that
תורת כהנים. Toras Kohanim. Anyway, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. So
he's saying the non-Jew is saying these things and he sort of
is like unwittingly saying things that make them make it halachically problematic.
Okay, so he says so he says that, so he says
so keep on going. או של נטע רבעי הן, o shel neta
revai hen, or which should have been said by the ערלה, orla,
or they're within the fourth year of the tree being planted. Okay,
לא אמר
כלום, lo amar klum, he didn't say anything. You don't have to
worry about his testimony. לא נתכוין אלא להשביח מקחו, lo niskavein ela
l'hashbiach mikcho, he was only trying to you know he was only
trying to say that look how good this these wares are that
I have and therefore it's not מסיח לפי תומו, masiach l'fi tumo,
there's another reason why he's saying these and why it might not
be accurate. Okay, he thinks if I say they're from this you
know protected field or they're from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or they're
from a young tree, maybe those are things that in his mind
make it better and therefore it's not a מסיח לפי תומו, masiach
l'fi tumo, there's other things which might which might mean that we
can't trust what he's saying. Now, how is that relevant? I don't
know, how is that relevant? Yeah, that's a question too, like if
it's שמיטה shmita who cares if it's a non-Jew. All right, fine,
we're not doing הלכות שמיטה, hilchos shmita, that is correct, it's good
to point that out. Now, the question is what how's this relevant?
Okay, there anyway we're being מחמיר, machmir, we're not, you know, so
because we so here so he's saying something that makes it worse.
Here he's saying something that makes it like better. I mean, excuse
me, there we're being מקל, meikel, you know, we're disregarding what he's
saying and we're able to be lenient and eat the fruit. Right?
So you know so and so that's anyway different. Here you want
to you know here you want to here by if we disregard
him we'll be מחמיר, machmir, if we pay attention we'll be lenient.
But maybe that's the point, that if we disregard him, even if
what he is saying would make us have to be concerned לחומרא
l'chumra and we're willing to disregard him, how much more so should
we disregard him and we can't rely on him לקולא, l'kula, right?
You got it? If we can't be if we're not even going
to be מחמיר machmir based on what... what he says, how much
more so can we not be מיקל. meikel. But fine, but what
happens to the rule that you can rely on a non-Jew? So
רש"י Rashi points out is, yes, but what this is telling you
is, not when you have a reason to think he might be
lying. So we have a reason to think he might be lying
in the case of the fruit. Why do we have a reason
to think he might be lying in the first case? Because he,
exactly, because he's saying you better do it because if you don't
do it I'll kill you like I killed someone else. So therefore
he's just doing it to threaten the guy, right? And since he's
just doing it to threaten the guy, there is no reason to
assume that it necessarily, it's not a מסיח
לפי תומו.
mesiach
lefi tumo.
Even took him three years to figure that out?
What? Yeah, so that's an interesting question.
It took him about two minutes.
I know, exactly. But the point, maybe the reason it was taking
אביי Abaye so long is you realize that the result of this
is that the woman couldn't remarry. So maybe אביי Abaye realized the
relevance of this and was, didn't want to give her an answer
because he was trying to find a way to make it מותר,
mutar, right?
But alright, but she went to רב יוסף Rav Yosef she got
a faster answer, but the answer was it's אסור. assur. The answer
was you can't remarry, so that doesn't do her a lot of
good. So it could be, it could be like אביי Abaye also
realized this but maybe was trying to find a way to be
מיקל meikel regardless.
Okay, even though he was very specific and there really was a
guy.
Right, that's the thing, you could say that he's so specific and
the guy hasn't been seen in three years, right? So maybe that,
right like, okay it's one thing to say I killed somebody else.
If he said I gave, I killed a particular person and he
hasn't been seen in three years, well again you're right, that's exactly
true. It's a good, a better reason to assume he was telling
the truth. Okay, so this puts a limit on the idea of
believing a non-Jew מסיח לפי תומו mesiach lefi tumo when there is
a reason to think that he is lying. Let's continue.
Now,
now we're going to have some cases where they did believe again,
going back to believing the non-Jew.
אבא יודן איש צידן, Abba Yudan Ish Tzaidan, אבא יודן Abba Yudan
from צידן, Tzaidan, אמר amar said the following: מעשה בישראל ואינו יהודי
שהיו מהלכין בדרך, Maaseh b'Yisrael v'Akum she-hayu m'halechin baderech, a Jew and
a non-Jew were going on the way.
ובא עכו"ם, Uba Akum, like it's set up for a joke. ובא
עכו"ם ואמר Uba Akum v'amar and the non-Jew came and said, חבל
על יהודי. Chaval al Yehudi.
And he gave, so we saw him going with ראובן Reuven on
a trip and then he came back from the trip and ראובן
Reuven wasn't with him and he said, חבל על יהודי שהיה עמי
בדרך, Chaval al Yehudi she-hayah imi baderech, I lost my place, שהיה
עמי בדרך שמת בדרך וכבר קברתיו, she-hayah imi baderech she-meis baderech u'kvar
tiv, woe to that Jew that was with me on our trip,
that he died on the way and I had to bury him.
והשיאו אשתו, V'hisyu ishto, they married off his wife. מסיח לפי תומו,
mesiach lefi tumo, fine.
Did they check if there was actually a grave over there?
What? Apparently not. Apparently not. Now there's going to be a little
discussion at the end about how much do you check, but even
there that's not checking the facts, it's just, you know, asking the
witness a few times just to make sure his story is consistent,
right? Again, obviously nowadays they would try to check, you know, as
much as possible, okay? But it is a good point that Michael
makes, which is there's no indication here of any attempt to try
to be מברר mevarev the facts. Right, we could assume that it
wasn't easy or maybe it was even difficult to do that, but
it's a good point that doesn't even address that issue. Okay. ושוב
מעשה בקולר של בני אדם, V'shuv maaseh b'kolar shel b'nei adam, another
story which was, was a group of people שהיו מהלכין לאנטוכיא, she-hayu
m'halchin l'Antuchya,
they were going to אנטוכיא, Antuchya, Antioch, ובא עכו"ם אחריהם ואמר uba
Akum achareihem v'amar and another non-Jew came and he wasn't even walking
with them, he just came back from the same place, אמר amar
and he said, חבל על קולר של בני אדם שמתו וכבר קברתים,
Chaval al kolar shel b'nei adam she-meisu u'kvar tim, woe to the
group of people
that they all died and I buried them. והשיאו נשיהם, V'hisyu nesheihem,
and they married off their wives. ושוב מעשה בשישים בני אדם, V'shuv
maaseh b'shishim b'nei adam, and another story of sixty people שהיו מהלכין
לכרקום ביתר, she-hayu m'halchin l'Karkom Beitar, they were going to this place
of כרקום ביתר, Karkom Beitar, ובא עכו"ם ואמר uba Akum v'amar and
a non-Jew came and said, חבל על שישים בני אדם שהיו מהלכין
בדרך ביתר, Chaval al shishim b'nei adam she-hayu m'halchin b'derech Beitar, woe
to the sixty people that were going the way of ביתר, Beitar,
שמתו וכבר קברתים, she-meisu u'kvar tim, that they died and I buried
them. והשיאו נשיהם, V'hisyu nesheihem, and they married off their wives. So
after telling us cases where we're afraid that the non-Jew might be
lying in a particular circumstance, it ends by a series of cases
where just any, you know, no special case, סתם stam non-Jew says
I saw them and they died, and, and we believe him. סתם
stam case of מסיח לפי תומו, mesiach lefi tumo, right? And, you
know, it gets also back to the earlier discussion about what is
considered נתכוון להעיד, nitkavein l'haid, where the גמרא Gemara says that even
if he's coming and saying, you know, let me, you know, he
wants to explicitly inform the wife and let her know, you know,
that wasn't considered to be נתכוון להעיד. nitkavein l'haid. So the גמרא
Gemara is willing to be pretty broad in terms of accepting the
testimony of the non-Jew. Okay, yes.
In terms of death, you know, could you also have questions like,
oh could it be כמדומה לו, k'midumeh lo, but over here it
can't be כמדומה לו k'midumeh lo if he actually buried them. You
know what I mean? So that also like, you know, sheds light
as to...
What, what do you mean?
I'm trying to... Remember we said like, you know, about death, like,
you know, how do you know the guy's dead?
Right, right, exactly. These are cases about who do you believe, not,
not whether you can assume the guy is dead.
And we basically sort
of, you know, do rely on... Yeah, I mean we do. I
mean these came up, you know, as having a whole talk with
Jonathan the other day about these, I mean they have come, I
mean there's a whole book about how they dealt with these in
the 9/11 cases, you know, and I mean, I mean, yes, these
come up, sadly these type of, these גמרות Gemaras are used a
good deal in particular, you know, in cases...
So we do rely on מסיח לפי תומו?
mesiach lefi tumo? Yeah, totally, yeah, uh-huh, and even more.
Yeah, I mean that's interesting too. I was wondering about the phrase
קולר kolar because קולר kolar often means
like, like chains. Right, I don't know what Soncino says or any,
I mean what Steinsaltz says or anybody else.
Also, also, also I
misexplained, right, I I I said כרכום ביתר, Karkom Beytar, כרכום Karkom
is not the name of a place, כרכום Karkom means like the
besieged city. So in both of these cases it is worth mentioning,
if קולר kolar does mean that they were prisoners, so in both
of these cases there are circumstances which is reasonable to assume that
something had happened. Like if you get a whole group of prisoners,
you know, it's more likely that they all will have died as
opposed to just a normal group of people. You have people that
are heading to a city that's under siege, you know, it's more
likely that they'll die than under normal circumstances. So one does, it's
not clear to what degree those context is part of what gave,
you know, believability to his claim.
Rabban Gamliel when he was
with him on the road. Yeah, the other one he was just
with him on the road, that's right, but it was only one
person, right?
I guess people shackled with collars. Shackled with collars, right?
Both of those
and talks about going to a dangerous zone.
Dangerous zone, right. So again, it's not exactly clear how much that
factored into the position here. Let's take a look.
Like the English word collar, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
All right, so let's take the next משנה, Mishna, מעידים לאור הנר
או לאור הלבנה. Ma'idim le'or haner o le'or halevana. So now we
get back to not who do you believe but what constitutes witnessing
something. So before we talked about like the guy was in a
dangerous situation where you can assume he died or maybe you might
assume he died. Now we're talking about how well did you see
him? Okay, even if you only saw the person by candlelight or
by moonlight. So you have to see his face, right? But maybe
even through limited light. ומשיאין על פי בת קול, Umasin al pi
bat kol, and you can marry based on a heavenly voice. So
that's not what a בת קול bat kol means. Actually look up
רש"י, Rashi, בת קול, bat kol, שמעו קול צועק פלוני מת ולא
ראו אדם בעצמו. sham'u kol tso'ek Ploni met velo ra'u adam be'atsmo.
So בת קול bat kol actually, this is important to know in
terms of because בת קול bat kol is so much used in
the בבלי Bavli to mean a heavenly voice, but that's not really
its original meaning. Its original meaning means a disembodied voice, okay? It's
just the voice without seeing the source from where it's emitted. Okay,
so sometimes בת קול bat kol can even mean like a rumor
went around or a report went around, right, as opposed to a
voice came out of heaven. All right, so בת קול, bat kol,
so that's what it means. You can marry somebody if you heard
a voice even if you didn't see who was saying it. Once
you can believe anybody, so who cares who's saying it, right? So
even if you just heard a voice. מעשה באחד, Ma'aseh be'echad, there's
a story about a person שמע מראש ההר, shama me'rosh hahar, he's
heard at the top of a mountain ואמר איש פלוני בן פלוני
ממקום פלוני מת. ve'amar Ish Ploni ben Ploni mimakom Ploni met. Okay,
so-and-so the son of so-and-so has died. והלכו ולא מצאו שם אדם
Vehalechu velo matsu sham adam
and they went to see who had said it, and by the
time they got there nobody was there. So here you have a
case, Michael, of going and trying to investigate the facts to some
degree. והשיאו את אשתו. Vehisi'u et ishto. And even though they couldn't
find the person to get any more information and they just had
the voice, that was enough. Okay, והשיאו את אשתו. vehisi'u et ishto.
ושוב מעשה, Veshuv ma'aseh,
of course you could say, well what if he's a non-Jew, is
that מסיח לפי תומו? mesiach lefi tumo? But nevertheless, you know, you
try to find out more information, but if you can't, that is
enough. ושוב מעשה בצלמון, Veshuv ma'aseh beTsalmon,
there was a story in צלמון, Tsalmon, באחד שאמר אני איש פלוני
בן איש פלוני
נשכני נחש. be'echad she'amar ani Ish Ploni ben Ish Ploni nashchani nachash.
I so-and-so the son of so-and-so, I've just been bitten by a
poisonous snake. והרי אני מת, Veharei ani met, and I am dying.
והלכו ולא הכירוהו, Vehalechu velo hikiruhu,
they went and by the time they got there they could not
tell who he was because, you know, his features had changed, you
know, had bloated or something. והלכו והשיאו את אשתו. Vehalechu vehisi'u et
ishto. They married off his wife. So what you see here again
is, on the one hand, an important point about trying to get
more information if possible, right, which raises that point, and then also
the point we made before about like maybe supporting evidence about the
context that it was a time of war and so on, if,
you know, that wasn't said explicitly but that might have been somewhat
implicit. So you try to sort of look at those things. But
in cases where you can't find out anything more, we're being very
very liberal in terms of what constitutes, you know, testimony that we
will marry off the woman.
But then there are the repercussions, right? Like you know, if the
guy comes back later then you know.
Yeah, exactly. Part of what it is, you know, that has not
been mentioned for a while in this גמרא, Gemara, but yes, there's
the earlier פרק perek that if it turns out that he's alive
there's all those negative consequences that the wife will have to suffer
if she
remarried. אמר רבה בר שמואל, Amar Rabba bar Shmuel, תנא, tana, we
taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, בית שמאי אומרים אין משיאין על פי
בת קול. Beit Shammai omerim ein mesi'in al pi bat kol. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says if you just have a disembodied voice you
cannot let the woman marry off. ובית הלל אומרים משיאין על פי
בת קול, VeBeit Hillel omerim mesi'in al pi bat kol, you can.
So מאי קמשמע לן מתניתין? mai kamashmalan matnitin? So big deal, it's
a בית הלל, Beit Hillel, who cares, we got a סתם משנה,
stam mishna, of course. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא קמשמע לן
דאי משתכח סתמא דאין משיאין, ha kamashmalan de'i mishtachach stama de'ein mesi'in,
to tell you that if you find another סתם, stam, not משנה
mishna but ברייתא braisa or some other source that says don't marry
off, don't say, oh well that goes up against our משנה, mishna,
maybe the הלכה halacha isn't so clear. No, בית שמאי היא, Beit
Shammai hi, you should know it's בית שמאי Beit Shammai and you
should know to be able to bracket it and put it aside.
Which is interesting because, you know, that's the question is asked in
the משניות mishnayot in עדויות, Eduyot, why did we mention a דעת
יחיד da'at yachid if we're not going to פסקן pasken like it?
And there are two answers to that question. One answer is because
we want that opinion recorded so we might be able to go
back to it בשעת הדחק, be'sha'at hadechak, right, which is embracing the
multiple opinions. And the other
reason is... recorded so that if anybody comes and claims that this
is the הלכה, halachah, we can sort of marginalize it and bracket
it and say, yeah, you're going by a דעת יחיד Da'as Yachid
that's already been rejected. So that actually the point of recording a
דעת יחיד Da'as Yachid is for the purpose of being able to
remove it from the system, not include it within the system, to
be able to push it out. No, I don't think both are
true, I think those are very opposite approaches. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is saying here about בית שמאי Beis Shammai about this.
It's important to note that this opinion is בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
so if you ever hear somebody else saying this opinion, you'll be
able to dismiss it. You'll be able to say, yeah, it's בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, we don't פסקן pasken like that. That's point number
one. Point number two is of course it's a little bit interesting,
I can't say ironic because sometimes people say ironic to mean the
exact opposite of ironic, they mean it's coincidental. It's very apropos, that's
ironic. Exactly, it's highly appropriate that remember when בית הלל Beis Hillel
and בית שמאי Beis Shammai were arguing who the הלכה halachah is
like, a בת קול Bas Kol comes out and says הלכה halachah
is like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So here בית שמאי Beis Shammai
are saying we don't go by a בת קול Bas Kol and
בית הלל Beis Hillel say we do go by a בת קול.
Bas Kol. It's not the same בת קול, Bas Kol, but I
couldn't resist making that point.
Yes,
you need both those approaches even though they are polarized. In other
words, certain in certain contexts, certain times you'll need to be inclusive
and sometimes you'll need to be exclusive. Right, yes, correct, correct, correct.
All right, ואזלו ולא אשכחו, va-azlu v'lo ashkechu, they went and they
did not find the person who had made this announcement. ודילמא שיד
הוה, v'dilma sheid hava, maybe how do you know it was a
person, maybe it was a demon? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Rav,
therefore demons lie?
Yes, exactly, demons always want to create problems. Okay, אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב שראו לו דמות אדם, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav she-ra'u
lo d'mus adam, he looked like a person. So, אינהו נמי דמו,
inhu nami damu, they also look like persons. דחזייה בבבואה, d'chazyei b'vavu'eh,
you saw a shadow. אינהו נמי אית להו בבבואה, inhu nami is
lehu bavu'eh, don't they also have shadows? דחזייה בבבואה דבבואה, d'chazyei b'vavu'eh
d'vavu'eh, you saw a shadow of a shadow. Okay, ודילמא לדידהו אית
להו בבבואה, v'dilma l'didehu is lehu bavu'eh, I don't know what a
shadow of a shadow is. Okay, ודילמא לדידהו אית להו בבבואה דבבואה,
v'dilma l'didehu is lehu bavu'eh d'vavu'eh, maybe they also have it? אמר
רב חנינא אמר רבי יונתן שידא, Amar Rav Chanina Amar Rabi Yonasan
shida, no, יונתן Yonasan the demon said to me, בבואה אית להו
בבואה דבבואה לית להו, bavu'eh is lehu bavu'eh d'vavu'eh leis lehu, that
demons have shadows, they don't have shadow of shadows. Okay, ודילמא צרה
הוי, v'dilma tzara havei,
maybe it was the co-wife? Could have said also, you know, who
we would not believe that has any, because even if you know
we don't worry about the מסיח לפי תומו misiach lefi tumo idea
again, you know, what constitutes מסיח לפי תומו misiach lefi tumo might
be a very broad category, so we're not going to worry about
the non-Jew case, but there are people that we don't believe regardless,
like the co-wife. Apparently we couldn't tell enough from some distance that
it was a male voice, you know, and sometimes you know, sometimes
men
have high-pitched voices, sometimes women have low-pitched voices, so maybe it was
a co-wife. So, צרה דשידא? tzara d'shida?
No. So the גמרא Gemara says תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל בשעת סכנה
כותבין ונותנין אף על פי שאין מכירין, Tana d'vei Rabi Yishmael b'sha'as
sakana kosvin v'nosnin af al pi she-ein makirin, at a time of
danger you can go ahead and write and give a גט get
even though you don't know the person. Now that's an analogous argument,
it's not the same point. The case there is if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, בשעת סכנה, b'sha'as sakana, שדי מסוכן, shadi mesukan, such
as somebody you hear a voice similar coming from a well saying
I'm ראובן בן שמעון, Reuven ben Shimon, write a גט get and
give it to my wife. Again, the reason somebody is saying that
is probably to save her from יבום yibum situations. וסמכינן עליה בכל
דבריו שאמר אני הוא פלוני בן פלוני. v'samchinan alei b'chol devarav she-omer
ani hu ploni ben ploni.
So even though you haven't you can't see him and you don't
recognize him, you trust it because otherwise, you know, you have no
choice, otherwise he's going to die and you won't have a chance
to give the wife a גט, get, so you don't have the
luxury of getting more data, you can rely on that. So הכא
נמי כשעת סכנה דמיא שאם לא תאמין לזה לא תמצא אחר ותשב
עגונה, hacha nami k'sha'as sakana damya she-im lo sa'amin l'zeh lo simtza
acher v'seishev aguna, right? So here everything, so it's again, it's not
סכנה sakana the person, some person is in danger, but the point
is what choice do we have? If we don't have any other
choices, then we can assume that if somebody says this is who
they are, that's who they are. Okay, or I guess actually it's
a little different because here the person didn't say who they were,
they just said so-and-so died, right, but and they didn't necessarily even
give their own name. But nevertheless, we can make a reasonable assumption
here and we don't have to worry that it's one of the
five people who דווקא davka we can't believe. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar
Rabi Akiva, now don't tell this to the צרות tzaros and to
the mother-in-laws and daughter-in-laws and they'll go on mountaintops and start making
announcements. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabi Akiva, said רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva,
כשירדתי לנהרדעא, keshe-yaradti l'Neharde'a, when I went down to נהרדעא Neharde'a לעבר
השנה, le'aver ha-shanah,
to make a leap year, again quite fascinating, he's doing it in
בבל, Bavel, right? The phrase ירדתי yaradti of course because, you know,
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to other ארצות aratzos you speak about doing
ירידה. yerida. Right, this came up before, we quoted it earlier, about
that sometimes you can do קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh in בבל Bavel
if there is not a similar type of, you know, people of
authority in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Of course it's funny, רבי עקיבא
Rabi Akiva was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he left ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael in order to do this. Anyway, that's fascinating in terms
of issues of קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh or עיבור שנה. ibbur shanah.
מצאתי נחמיה איש בית דלי, Matzasi Nechemya ish Beis Deli, I found
this person נחמיה Nechemya from בית דלי. Beis Deli. אמר לי שמעתי
שאין משיאין את האשה בארץ ישראל על פי עד אחד אלא רבי
יהודה בן בבא. Amar li shamati she-ein masi'in es ha-ishah b'Eretz Yisrael
al pi eid echad ela Rabi Yehuda ben Bava. I heard that
now this is really fascinating because you're hearing that everything we've been
assuming until this point about the broad acceptance of testimony, and remember
it started with בית הלל, Beis Hillel, I want to remind you
that it started with בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai a discussion of harvesting the wheat and coming back from this
wheat harvest, and that was
about... Until then we've just simply slid into this idea of not
just the wife, anybody, and not just an adult male, a woman,
a minor, a non-Jew, no not a גוי. goy. So we've all
of a sudden assumed like all of a sudden you can believe
anyone, right? And when did all of this develop? Who decided this
or whatever? You know, I mean even the initial thing of believing
the wife was a whole debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and
בית שמאי Beis Shammai whether to leave it as a very narrow
circumstance. And now we're going to find out that this huge חידוש
chidush and innovation in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was only the position
of יהודה בן בבא. Yehuda ben Bava. Nobody else was doing this.
שמעתי שאין משיאין את האשה בארץ ישראל על פי עד אחד אלא
יהודה בן בבא. Shemati she-ein masi'in et ha-isha b'Eretz Yisrael al pi
ed echad ela Yehuda ben Bava. ונמתי לו, Ve-nomti lo, and I
said to him, that's a more archaic form of
אמרתי לו. amarti lo. ונמתי לו כן הדברים, Ve-nomti lo ken hadvarim,
that is correct. אמר לי, Amar li, he said to me, אמור
להם בשמי, Emor lahem bishmi, go tell them in my name, בארץ
ישראל אתם יודעים שהמדינה משובשת בגייסות, b'Eretz Yisrael atem yodeim sheha-medina m'shubashet
b'gaysot,
you know that this country is like, you know, has corrupt, I
mean but it's like you know is like whatever it's riddled, thank
you, excellent word, riddled with troops and you know and I can't
travel, it's very hard to travel so I can't go and testify
myself. But tell them the following in my name. מקובלני מרבן גמליאל
הזקן, Mekublani me-Rabban Gamliel Hazaken, I have a tradition from the elder
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel going way back, שמשיאין את האשה על פי
עד אחד, she-masi'in et ha-isha al pi ed echad, that you can
marry off a woman based on one witness and that is not
just a position that should be just a יהודה Yehuda position. And
notice this isn't even the question about women and non-Jews and minors,
just basically somebody who isn't the wife, עד אחד, ed echad, okay?
וכשבאתי והרציתי את הדברים לפני רבן גמליאל, U-kshe-bati v-hirtzeiti et hadvarim lifnei
Rabban Gamliel,
I came and I told this to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, not
רבן גמליאל הזקן, Rabban Gamliel Hazaken, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the younger,
not the older, right? The one that was in the generation of
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. שמח לי דברי, Samach li d'varai,
he rejoiced with my words, because especially it was in the name
of his ancestor. ואמר מצאנו חבר לרבי יהודה בן בבא, Ve-amar matzanu
chaver l'Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava, we have now found a support to
a to רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava, a you
know a supporting testimony. מתוך הדבר נזכר רבן גמליאל, Mitoch hadavar nizkar
Rabban Gamliel, and then because they were talking about this and that
this is the now we have somebody that backs this up and
you see clearly they wanted this to be the הלכה, halacha, but
they maybe felt that they did not have enough to go on
to establish this as the הלכה halacha and now they had this
ancient tradition that they heard to reinforce it and to support it.
And in the middle of this of this discussion נזכר רבן גמליאל
שנהרגו הרוגים בתל ארזה, nizkar Rabban Gamliel she-nehergu harugim b'Tel Arza, he
remembered that there had been these reports about people that had been
killed in תל ארזה Tel Arza and nothing had been done about
it because apparently the reports about it had come based on עד
אחד. ed echad. והשיא רבן גמליאל נשיהם על פי עד אחד. Ve-hisi
Rabban Gamliel nisheihem al pi ed echad. So on the basis of
this report that they got from נהרדעא, Nehardea, they were able to
really establish this as the הלכה halacha and then to go ahead
and act on it. Right, it's amazing like what if this one
event had not occurred? Right, and this is sort of the whole
message also of מסכת עדיות, Masechet Eduyot, the importance of gathering up
all these testimonies so that this doesn't get lost. והוחזקו, Ve-huchzeku,
it had for a while been minority but then it was reinforced
and it was given backing. והוחזקו להיות משיאין, Ve-huchzeku l'hiyot masi'in, and
then that led to establishing the practice. So this is like really
fascinating where you see the whole history of a הלכה halacha and
a הלכתית halachic innovation, you know, and how it all sort of
developed here. So once that was true and it went from theory
to practice, the practice became
established, להיות משיאין עד מפי עד, l'hiyot masi'in ed mipi ed, and
not only עד אחד, ed echad, but now we're even going to
go even further than everything we said before. Not only עד אחד,
ed echad, not only women and non-Jews and children, but hearsay testimony,
עד מפי עד, ed mipi ed, you didn't even claim to see
it yourself.
ומפי עבד, U-mipi eved, and a slave, ומפי אשה, ve-mipi isha, which
we had been saying, interesting that that comes after the עבד, eved,
ומפי שפחה, mipi shifcha, and from a non-Jew and from a slave
and from a slave woman. Okay, so once we established it, we
didn't leave it at עד אחד, ed echad, we included any person
to testify and we haven't mentioned slaves until this point, you know,
the גמרא Gemara doesn't assume that just because a non-Jew is believed,
a slave is believed. The גמרא Gemara is very negative attitudes towards
slaves even worse than non-Jews at times. Okay, and number number two,
the big חידוש chidush we haven't heard yet is hearsay testimony.
רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע אומרים, Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua omrim, so that's
like an amazing story about how this whole principle got established. Now
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say, who were
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva רביים, Rebbeim, remember, so this was probably before
this event.
They say אין משיאין את האשה על פי עד אחד,
ein masi'in et ha-isha al pi
ed echad, you cannot marry a woman off on one testimony. They
disagreed with רבי יהודה בן בבא's Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava position. רבי
עקיבא אומר לא על פי אשה ולא על פי עבד ולא על
פי שפחה ולא על פי קרובים. Rabbi Akiva omer lo al pi
isha ve-lo al pi eved ve-lo al pi shifcha ve-lo al pi
krovim. You can do it על פי עד אחד, al pi ed
echad, but not a woman or slaves or not relatives. So here
you have all these restrictions, you know, so what's going on here?
Didn't we just say that they had they made a wide allowance?
So the גמרא Gemara asks this. וסבר רבי עקיבא על פי אשה
לא, Ve-savar Rabbi Akiva al pi isha lo, does רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva really say you can't do it based on a woman? והתניא
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר. Ve-hatanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer. משום
רבי עקיבא. mishum Rabbi Akiva. רבי שמעון אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Elazar says
in the name of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אשה נאמנת להביא גיטה
מקל וחומר, isha ne'emenet lehavi gita mi-kal va-chomer, a woman could bring
her own גט get and testify that it was signed and sealed
correctly, בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, befanai nechtav uvfanai nechtam, based on a
קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal va-chomer? ומה נשים
שאמרו חכמים אין נאמנות לומר מת בעלה, u-ma nashim she-amru chachamim ein
ne'emanot lomar met ba'alah,
the women that are not allowed to be believed to say that
a woman's husband died, right, the co-wife and the mother-in-law and whatever,
נאמנות להביא גיטיהן, ne'emanot lehavi gite'en, they can bring a גט get
for a woman and say that it was done correctly because the
actual written and signed גט get supports their statement, so they are
believed there, זו שנאמנת לומר מת בעלה, zo she-ne'emenet lomar met ba'alah,
a woman who is believed to say her husband died, אינו דין
שנאמנת להביא גיטה, eino din she-ne'emenet lehavi gitah, how much more so
should she be believed to bring her own גט. get. So the
גמרא Gemara points out this whole issue about women testifying about the
death of a husband was a specific set of women. So implicit
in that statement is נשים שאמרו חכמים הוא דלא מהימני, nashim she-amru
chachamim hu de-lo meheimnei, the five groups of, the five types of
women, you know, co-wife and mother-in-law, whatever, they're the ones that aren't
believed. אשה בעלמא מהימנא, isha be'alma meheimna, implicitly a woman is believed.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva clearly holds a woman is believed. So
לא קשיא כאן קודם שהחזיקו כאן מאחרי שהחזיקו, lo kashya kan kodem
she-hecheziku kan me-acharei she-hecheziku,
it all is before or after the story with רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel and the story about רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva hearing this report in נהרדעא. Neharde'a. So this is amazing, right,
the end of the משנה Mishnah is an early layer, right, imagine
this, right, the early layer was we'd establish, right, that a woman
is believed. Imagine that we don't have any of our פרק, perek,
right, we said way back בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel u-Beit
Shammai, there was a debate about do you believe a woman, a
wife, not a woman, a wife in general? בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says in general yes, בית הלל Beit Hillel says only in narrow
cases and בית הלל Beit Hillel rules like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
fine. At that point, all we had established was that a wife
is believed. You all just took, you know, we slid it under,
you know, the radar that we then assume that we're going to
believe anyone, okay? But no, all we really had established at that
early בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u-Beit Shammai stage is the
wife is believed. If you had come then and read the last
line of this משנה, Mishnah, you'd find out there's a, there's a
debate about do you believe people other than the wife? רבי אליעזר
ורבי יהושע Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Yehoshua says, no, you don't believe עד
אחד, ed echad, the only person you believe is the wife or
two עדים. edim. It's a special דין din with the wife. Comes
along רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, you
believe עד אחד, ed echad, but only a kosher עד, ed, only
a man, right, only an adult male, right? So, and that's the
whole debate and that's... okay, that would have been very limited. And
now we find out all of that was before they got this
report from בבל. Bavel. They got this report from בבל Bavel that
to support a position of יהודה בן בבא, Yehuda ben Bava, to
support an idea that you marry off based on עד אחד, ed
echad, okay, and then רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel acted on it, it
became practice. Once it became established as practice, not only did they
believe עד אחד, ed echad, but they believed a wide category, right,
they believed even, they believed women and minors and non-Jews and slaves
and they even believed hearsay testimony. So it's really like, like breathtaking
how radically, right, the discourse changed as a, on the basis of
that. And this last line in the משנה, Mishnah, like is a
vestige of that earlier stage which we wouldn't have even been aware
of, right? So it's quite fascinating for the, how much we see
about הלכה halakhah history and development in this little גמרא Gemara here.
Okay, next משנה, Mishnah, last משנה. Mishnah. אמרו לו מעשה בבני לוי
שהלכו לצועה עיר תמרים, amru lo ma'aseh bi-vnei Levi she-halchu litzvo'a ir
tamarim,
so they said to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right, who said that
that you don't believe,
the early רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva before he retracted, who said you
don't believe women. So they said to רבי עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: מעשה
בבני לוי, ma'aseh bi-vnei Levi, there's a story about these people called
בני לוי, Bnei Levi, שהלכו לצועה עיר תמרים, she-halchu litzvo'a ir tamarim,
they went to צועה Tzo'a the city of palm trees, of, the
date palms, right, וחלה אחד מהם, ve-chalah echad me-hem, and one of
them died, והביאוהו בפונדק, ve-hiv'ihu befundak, and they had him stay at
an inn while they went on their trip. One of them got
sick, I say, I'm sorry, I said died. I was anticipating the
end of the story. One of them got sick, I ruined the
story, right, 'cause you don't know, you never know how these things
are going to end. Anyway, one of them got sick so they
put him up in an inn as they went on their journey,
ובחזרתם, u-vachazaratam, and when they returned, אמרו לפונדקית, amru le-fundakit, they said
to the inn woman, איה חברינו? ayeh chaveirenu?
Where is our colleague? נמה להם, namah lahem, she said to them,
מת וקברתיו, met u-kivartiv, I died and I buried him, והשיאו את
אשתו, ve-hisi'u et ishto, and on the basis of this they married
off the wife. So you see רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you can
believe a woman. ולא תהא כוהנת כפונדקית? velo tehei kohenet ke-fundakit?
And should not a בת כוהן, bat kohen, like, you know, be
as good as this innkeeper? If you can believe an innkeeper, how
much from, you know, there are a lot of women in our
community that are at a, you know, that are, uh, you know,
that are more believable than her. Well, what about, you know, people
with יחוס yichus and so on? How could you say you don't
believe women if you even believe this woman innkeeper? אמר להם, amar
lahem, he said back to them, אמר להם amar lahem it should
be, לשתהא כפונדקית נאמנת. le-she-tihiye ke-fundakit ne'emenet. If they will be like
this innkeeper, they'll be believed. What, why, what was special about the
פונדקית? fundakit? הפונדקית הוציאה להם מקלו ותרמילו, ha-fundakit hotzi'ah lahem maklo ve-tarmilo,
she didn't just say it, she brought out his effects: his staff,
right, like תמר, Tamar, his staff and his sack, וספר תורה שהיה
בידו, ve-sefer Torah she-hayah be-yado, and a ספר תורה Sefer Torah that
wasn't in the יהודה ותמר Yehuda ve-Tamar story. So he brought out
his effects.
Oh, you're good, Rabbi. You picked up the eating of the lettuce
from yesterday, the חסה. chasa. Okay, anyway. All right, I did not
pick that up at all. Anyway, so here is the early רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says you don't believe women before, notice by
the way the intellectual honesty that even though רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
said you don't believe women, he came back and he reported to
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel this other testimony, right, which led to a
complete reversal of the practice or not a, you know, or at
least a very a huge broadening of the practice. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא, Gemara, קח ב עמוד ב. Kuf Ches
Beis Amud Beis.
What's an idiom כוהנית? Kohenis? Is that is that a Yiddishism?
Yeah, yeah, sometimes בת כהן bas Kohen it says כוהנית. Kohenis. Oh.
Okay.
So, okay. So מאי גרעותא דפונדקית? mai geruta depundakis? What what would
be the problem with the like what's the קל וחומר kal vachomer
they were making? If you believe an innkeeper, you should certainly believe
like a good Jewish you know, like a good you know a
good Jewish woman, a בת כהן bas Kohen or something. So what's
what's wrong with an innkeeper? Is she just from like a low
lower social strata which would have been a completely reasonable way of
reading it like if you believe this you know person from lower
classes, you know, it's a sort of that sort of class bias
and certainly how could you know you should believe you should believe
other women, people certainly women from higher classes. Like how could you
not believe other women? So but anyway the גמרא Gemara says what
was the problem with her that they made this קל וחומר? kal
vachomer? So אמר רב כהנא פונדקית עובדת כוכבים היתה. amar Rav Kahana
pundakis ovedes kochavim haysah. Ah, it was even a non-Jew and they
believed her, right, which is basically interesting. It's introducing into the earlier
stages, right, again the pre-reversal stages or the pre you know reporting
of and רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel action stages, the possibility of believing
a non-Jew as well, right? Notice that by the way, right, that
was not right that where did that sneak in that you believe
a non-Jew, when did that get established? So the גמרא Gemara is
weaving in that that was already a matter of debate at the
time of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay. פונדקית עובדת כוכבים היתה ומסיחה
לפי תומה היתה, pundakis ovedes kochavim haysah umesiacha lefi tumah haysah, זה
מקלו וזה תרמילו וזה קבר שקברתיו בו. ze maklo veze tarmilo veze
kever shekevartiv bo.
This is his staff and his sack and where I buried him.
וכן תניא בבריה דרב בנימין בר חייא, vechen tanya bevarya deRav Binyamin
bar Chiya, פונדקית עובדת כוכבים היתה ומסיחה לפי תומה היתה, pundakis ovedes
kochavim haysah umesiacha lefi tumah haysah, זה מקלו וזה תרמילו וזה קבר
שקברתיו
בו. ze maklo veze tarmilo veze kever shekevartiv bo.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא איכן חבירנו קא רמי לה?
veha aychan chaveirenu ka rami lah? But they said where's our friend?
So they wanted they were asking her for explicit report on his
fate which makes the גמרא's Gemara assuming is not מסיח לפי תומו.
mesiach lefi tumo. Again, it's very hard for me to know exactly
what constitutes מסיח לפי תומו mesiach lefi tumo because the גמרא Gemara
yesterday said that somebody comes back and says where's so-and-so's wife? I
want him to know that he died. Oh, that's not that's מסיח
לפי תומו, mesiach lefi tumo, that's not נתכוון להעיד. nitkaven lehaid. So
how is this any different? Where's our friend? So she told them
where the friend was. I don't exactly get you know exactly what
the line is.
No but it wasn't en passant yesterday. And it wasn't en passant
before what we had today before the משנה. Mishnah. I was walking
with so-and-so and he died and I buried him. Anyway, somehow because
it's maybe if it's clear that they're like we need to know,
that makes it like להעיד. lehaid. Like we need your testimony as
opposed to somebody even if they're intentionally informing as opposed to being
sort of like you know as opposed to being like quizzed you
know and as opposed to being you know sort of directly you
know put on the spot and asked, you know maybe that makes
it more of a type of like testimony. Okay, so that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So והא איכן חבירנו קא רמי לה? veha aychan
chaveirenu ka rami lah? And the fact that she's being like you
know drilled was the word I was looking for, that should make
it a no longer מסיח לפי תומו. mesiach lefi tumo. No. כיוון
דחזתינהו, keivan dechazatinhu, she saw them בכיה, bachya, crying, so excuse me,
כיוון דחזתינהו, keivan dechazatinhu, excuse me, she saw them, they they returned
to the inn בכיה. bachya. And then she started crying. Okay, and
then אמרו לה, amru lah, they said to then they said where's
our friend? אמרה להם מית וקברתיו. amrah lahem meis ukevartiv. So apparently
because she was dying first she was crying first and response to
seeing them that made it a מסיח לפי תומו. mesiach lefi tumo.
It was a it was a thing that happened naturally. It didn't
happen in the context of being drilled for
information.
Go in a similar position, right? We only like you know like
reminds me of that like we see her crying and
they're yeah yeah right, but that's when somebody is coming into the
court. Okay, so here presumably it stops being מסיח לפי תומו mesiach
lefi tumo when somebody is being you know directly queried and drilled
but if it was a natural response that's okay. Okay and all
the other cases were natural responses. Somebody wasn't responding to being put
in you know you know into being questioned as opposed so that's
that seems to be something that would shift it into into no
longer מסיח לפי תומו. mesiach lefi tumo. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara continues. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, מעשה באחד שבא להעיד על
אשה לפני רבי טרפון. maaseh beachad sheba lehaid al ishah lifnei Rabbi
Tarfon. A man came to testify for a woman in front of
רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him,
בני היאך אתה יודע בעדות אשה זו? bni heich atah yodeiah be-eidus
ishah zu? How do you know regarding this testimony regarding this woman's
status? By the way, that's a phrase that we haven't seen so
much of but becomes a phrase used in a lot of other
גמרות, Gemoros, עדות אשה, eidus ishah, which does not mean the testimony
given by a woman but testimony for the in order to allow
a woman to remarry. And often it is used to discuss who
are the people that are believed לעדות אשה. le'eidus isha. For עדות
אשה eidus isha we believe an עד אחד, ed echad, עד מפי
עד, ed mipi ed, a שפחה, shifcha,
a non-Jew and so on. So that's an important to acknowledge, to
note that that's like a technical term that gets used in many
other contexts. So he said to him, היכן אתה יודע בעדות אשה
זו? heichan atah yodeia be'eidus isha zu? How do you know regarding
this woman's status that her husband died? אמר, amar, אני והוא היינו
הולכים בדרך, ani vehu hayinu holchim baderech, we were going on the
way, ורדף אחרינו גייס, veradaf achareinu gayas, and an army troop or
some type of a troop of bandits or whatever ran after us,
ונתלה ביכוש של זית, venitlah be'ichush shel zayis, and he sort of
grabbed onto a
branch of an olive tree, ופשחו, ufashcho, and he sort of tore
it off, והחזיר את הגייס אחוריו, vehechezir es hagayas achorav, and he
returned and he like beat them back somehow with his a branch.
I don't know how he managed to do that. אמרתי לו, amarti
lo, I said to him, אריה, Aryeh, יישר כוחך. yishar kochacha. So
you see יישר כוחך yishar kochacha is already in the גמרא. Gemara.
So we have יארצייט yortzeit and יישר כוח yishar kochach in the
גמרא Gemara today. Okay. So I said, and he said, you're a
lion, you managed to fight back those whole, those bandits. You know
strength be to you, that your strength be straight. אמר לי, amar
li, so he said back to me, מניין אתה יודע ששמי אריה?
minayin atah yodeia she'shmi Aryeh? How'd you know that was my name?
My name is אריה. Aryeh. כך קורין אותי בעירי, kach korin oti
be'iri, this is what they call me in my
city. יוחנן ברבי יהונתן, Yochanan brebi Yehonasan, אריה, Aryeh, מכפר שיחייא, mikfar
Shichayah, from the place שיחייא. Shichayah. Okay, so apparently אריה Aryeh was
yet to be a proper name but it was a nickname, okay,
and he had just mentioned like oh my god you have the
courage of a lion and he said you know what that actually
happens to be my nickname. Okay, so that was happened to also
be then highly identifying information about him, right? And then what happened?
לימים חלה, leyamim chalah,
and after a while then he got sick, ומת, umes, and he
died. So that's how I know who it was. This is how
I know who the guy was I was traveling with and I'm
telling you he died. והשיב רבי טרפון את האשה, veheshiv Rabbi Tarfon
es ha'ishah, and Rabbi Tarfon married off his wife. So that's a
straight case of an עד אחד ed echad with very specific and
concrete information. Not nearly a חידוש chiddush based on everything we've been
seeing until now. Okay. רבי טרפון לא בעי דרישה וחקירה, Rabbi Tarfon
lo ba'ei drishah vachakirah, now the גמרא Gemara also wants to clarify
again, you know, the range of what we could have gone with
this, what we could have demanded. A, we could have demanded it
be a male עד אחד, ed echad, we could have demanded we
don't even accept עד אחד, ed echad, we need two witnesses if
it's not the woman, if it's not the wife. But even we
accept עד אחד ed echad we could have demanded that it be
a normal like male kosher עד. ed. And now we're saying and
maybe we could have demanded that you go through a דרישה וחקירה,
drishah vachakirah, right? דרישה וחקירה drishah vachakirah is what you normally do
with witnesses, you know you drill them and you double check their
what they're saying and you know to make sure that you know
you're 100% certain that they're not that there's no mess ups in
their testimony. So that wasn't the impression we got. We got the
impression that somebody's just saying something in passing. You accept it as
soon as they say it. So now the גמרא Gemara is looking
at again a path that we didn't go down that we could
have gone down, that we just treated this as classic testimony and
demanded a classic עד אחד ed echad and demanded דרישה וחקירה. drishah
vachakirah. And now we're going to see that maybe Rabbi Tarfon did
need that in other cases. Rabbi Tarfon or the same case told
differently. רבי טרפון לא בעי דרישה וחקירה? Rabbi Tarfon lo ba'ei drishah
vachakirah? Did Rabbi Tarfon not require דרישה וחקירה? drishah vachakirah? והתניא, vehatanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. מעשה באחד שבא לפני רבי טרפון
להעיד עדות אשה, ma'aseh be'echad sheba lifnei Rabbi Tarfon le'haid eidus isha,
the same story but it ends a little different. אמר לו, amar
lo, בני היכן אתה יודע עדות זו? beni heichan atah yodeia eidus
zu? How do you know this testimony? אמר לו, amar lo, אני
והוא היינו הולכים בדרך ורדף אחרינו גייס ונתלה ביכוש של תאנה ופשחו
והחזיר את הגייס אחוריו, ani vehu hayinu holchim baderech veradaf achareinu gayas
venitlah be'ichush shel te'enah ufashcho vehechezir es hagayas achorav, so again he
grabbed the palm branch, the olive branch, and he beat them back.
אמרתי לו, amarti lo, אריה, Aryeh, יישר כוחך, yishar kochacha, wait one
minute, it was a תאנה, te'enah, was it? I missed that. Ah
now it makes a big difference. Okay fine. It was a תאנה
te'enah tree, it wasn't an olive tree. Okay fine. So okay fine,
it was a fig tree. אמרתי לו, amarti lo, יישר כוחך אריה.
yishar kochacha Aryeh. אמר לי, amar li, יפה כיוונת לשמי, yafeh kivanta
lishmi, he said back to me, yeah you know what you guessed
my name, שכך קורין אותי בעירי, she'kach korin oti be'iri, this is
what they call me in my city, יוחנן בן יהונתן אריה מכפר
שיחייא. Yochanan ben Yehonasan Aryeh mikfar Shichayah. לימים חלה, leyamim chalah, and
then he went ahead and he got sick, ומת umes and he
died. This was what he said to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. אמר,
amar, now here's how the story ends
different. אמר לו, amar lo, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said to him
then, not רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, excuse me, Rabbi Tarfon. Rabbi Tarfon
said to him, one minute, לא כך אמרת לי יוחנן בן יהונתן
מכפר שיחייא אריה? lo kach amarta li Yochanan ben Yehonasan mikfar Shichayah
Aryeh? Wait wait wait, what'd you say his name was? You said
it was אריה Aryeh from
כפר שיחייא, Kfar Shichayah, I thought you said אריה Aryeh was the
end of his name, I thought you said it was יוחנן בן
יהונתן Yochanan ben Yehonasan of כפר שיחייא Kfar Shichayah אריה. Aryeh.
So he was trying to see if he would like you know
adjust his testimony. You know one minute didn't you tell me the
name was a little different? אמר לו לא, amar leh lo, no
that's not what I said, אלא כך אמרתי לך יוחנן בן יהונתן
אריה מכפר שיחייא. ela kach amarti lecha Yochanan ben Yehonasan Aryeh mikfar
Shichayah. So he kept on like you know trying to go back
like they do this you know like when the police like are
trying you know to question a witness, you know they go back
over the same thing and have him say it again and to
make sure it doesn't get said differently each time as a
way of checking how consistent... fine.
The question is not this version versus the other version, it's within
this version the point was that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was trying
to trip
him up, see. "Wait a minute, didn't you say this?" whether he
would say, "Oh yeah, that is what I said" or whether he
would remain consistent. And he remained consistent in his story. ודקדק אותו
בשתים ובשלש פעמים, v'dikdek oto b'shtayim u'veshalosh p'amim,
two and three times he tried to make him trip up, וכיוון
את דבריו v'kiven et devarav and he remained consistent in his testimony,
and then והשיא רבן גמליאל את אשתו. v'hisi Rabban Gamliel et ishto.
So you see a very different idea we have never heard any
of this until now that you have to really do like a
drilling and rigorous in order to see if...
But simply, he said
the same thing three times. Yeah, but you want to make sure,
let's go over it again and let's go over it again and
presumably if there was any change, discrepancy, even if it was not
substantive, that would have he would have dismissed the testimony. We did
not get that attitude that you look for discrepancy and you throw
it out. We got the attitude that you look for where were
you? These... Yeah, but obviously this is not the same type of
דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. This is being used more loosely as meaning
a type of a drilling and a searching for discrepancy. Okay, and
that changes very much, that would have us dismiss a lot of
testimonies, because even people that are saying the truth, they don't always
say things over exactly the same way and they'll have slightly different
versions.
Sure they cannot touch that shadow that you saw.
Exactly. So here's a very different approach to where we could have
gone with all of this. So the Gemara says תנאי היא, tannai
hi, it's a debate of Tannaim, דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
Baraita, אין בודקין עדי נשים בדרישה וחקירה
דברי רבי עקיבא, ein bodkin edei nashim b'drisha v'chakira divrei Rabbi Akiva,
you do not check women who are testifying, and that's an עדות
אשה edut isha idea, about a woman's status, you do not have
them ask them
a very insightful type of investigation. Okay, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says. There's some question if this is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
or others have the גרסא, girsa,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva put don't have דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei Rabbi
Akiva, have a period and then it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva v'רבי
טרפון אומרים. Rabbi Tarfon omerim. But anyway, in our version it's רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the more lenient approach. דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei
Rabbi Akiva, רבי טרפון אומר בודקין, Rabbi Tarfon omer bodkin, you do
check. Okay, וקמיפלגי בדרבי חנינא, v'kamiflegi b'de'Rabbi Chanina, and this
so there's yes, there's a debate whether רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon demands
דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. What's this debate hinging on? רבי חנינא's Rabbi
Chanina statement. דאמר רבי חנינא דבר תורה אחד דיני ממונות ואחד דיני
נפשות בדרישה וחקירה. d'amar Rabbi Chanina dvar Torah echad dinei mamonot v'echad
dinei nefashot b'drisha v'chakira.
Biblically speaking you have to do, now this is talking about classic
דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. Where were you? What time was it? What
was the day? Basically location and place and time, not a whole
cross-examining. We're using דרישה וחקירה drisha v'chakira to mean like a cross-examining
and a reviewing and a being very,
like trying to see if the person will trip up. But classic
דרישה וחקירה drisha v'chakira means just identifying the time and place. So
whether דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, whether
capital cases or monetary cases need דרישה וחקירה, drisha v'chakira, שנאמר, shene'emar,
משפט אחד יהיה לכם, mishpat echad yihye lachem, one law, one procedure.
ומה טעם אמרו דיני ממונות אין צריכין דרישה וחקירה? u'mah ta'am amru
dinei mamonot ein tzrichin drisha v'chakira? Why do we not do it
by דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot? שלא תנעול
דלת בפני לווין, shelo tinol delet bifnei lovin, in order not
to lock the door in front of borrowers, because if creditors are
going to know that in order to collect they're going to have
to go through this like drill and this rigorous cross-examination
before they can prove that they're owed money, they won't lend money.
Okay, by the way,
the חקירות chakirot are the issue
about the time and the location. The דרישה drisha part is just
the general cross-examining. Okay, so דרישה וחקירה drisha v'chakira includes both the
specific of time and location, but the more issue that we're talking
about is the דרישה, drisha, is all of that cross-examining and checking
every detail. Okay, ובמאי קמיפלגי? u'vemai kamiflegi?
So now that's what we say by דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. So
how does that apply here? מר סבר כיון דאיכא כתובה למשקל כדיני
ממונות דמי, mar savar keivan d'ika ketubah lemishkal kedinei mamonot dami,
one says since you're going to collect the כתובה ketubah it's like
דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. ומר סבר כיון דקשרינן אשת איש לעלמא כדיני
נפשות דמי. u'mar savar keivan d'kashrinan eshet ish l'alma kedinei nefashot dami.
Now that is bizarre, because of course who cares if there's also
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot element? The bigger element is personal status
and that should require דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. So the point here
is that it's an excuse to, it's not really that it's דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. Nobody would say this is fundamentally a דיני ממונות
dinei mamonot case. But because we can frame it as that, that
gives us an out not to demand דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. And
this is like said explicitly if you look at this תוספות חד
מקמי Tosafot Chad Mi-Kamai here on the right. He says like this
at the end here: ומר סבר כיון דשרינן אשת איש לעלמא כדיני
נפשות דמיא והלכה כרבנן דרבי מנהו, u'mar savar keivan d'sharinan eshet ish
l'alma kedinei nefashot damya v'halacha k'rabbanan d'rabbi minhu, that you don't need
דרישה וחקירה. drisha v'chakira. ועוד כיון דמפי איש ומפי עבד ושפחה משיאין,
v'od keivan d'mipi ish u'mipi eved u'shifcha mas'in, once
this was all within this narrower context that you need a classic
עד אחד ed echad and you're doing classic... No, now we've like
totally expanded the rules of testimony here. משום תקנת עגונה, mishum takanat
agunah,
once because of עגונה agunah we've completely broadened it from this initial
approach, so הכילו ולא עבדינן דרישה וחקירה וכן פסק
הרמב"ם ז"ל.
hikilu v'lo avdinan drisha
v'chakira v'chen pasak haRambam zal.
Okay, and similarly, תוספות חד מקמי. Tosafot Chad Mi-Kamai. Also תוספות ישנים
Tosafot Yeshanim on the other side says ופסק רבינו תם דלא בעינן
דרישה וחקירה דהאי לאו כתנא קמא. u'pasak Rabbeinu Tam d'lo ba'inan drisha
v'chakira d'hai lav k'Tanna Kamma. So everybody goes with the flow here
because that is the flow. The flow is that we had... but
again, it's so fascinating to see the different approach to where we
could have gone with all of this. only with דרישה וחקירה derisha
vechakira and we wind up completely loosening all of these things, right?
Any type of witness,
slave, non-Jew, minor, woman, any type of witness, עד, ed, and not
only that, even hearsay testimony, and certainly not דרישה וחקירה, derisha vechakira,
which is a classic rigorous type of an approach to giving testimony.
And that's why the Gemara frames it as כתובה דיני ממונות Kesuvah
Dinei Mamonos as the way to say why we don't need it.
But ultimately, we don't need it because we are completely reshaping the
idea of עדות edus in this case. We're not trying to make
it fit a classic idea of עדות.
edus. Because it's דרבנן... de-Rabbanan...
yeah, I know, right, right. And now the Gemara ends, אמר רבי
אלעזר אמר רבי חנינא תלמידי חכמים מרבים שלום בעולם שנאמר וכל בנייך
לימודי ה' ורב שלום בנייך. Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar Rabbi Chanina Talmidei
Chachamim Marbim Shalom Ba'olam Shenemar Vechol Banayich Limudei Hashem Verav Shalom Banayich.
And of course, this is highly appropriate for the end of this,
some מסכתות masechtos like to end with אגדתא, aggadeta, although they don't
always. But of course, this is so highly appropriate because here, as
a result of all of this amazing innovation of the Sages and
the way the הלכה halacha went, it created a tremendous amount of
resolving of עגונה agunah situations, right? But through this really breathtaking sense
of innovation, and you really see it so powerful, this last דף,
daf, about how the history הלכה halacha developed, and you see the
paths it could have taken that it didn't take. Okay, הדרן עלך
האשה בתרא וסליקא לה מסכת יבמות. Hadran Alach Ha'ishah Basra Vesalika Lah
Maseches Yevamos. יישר כח Yasher koach to everybody. I will say we
have one minute left, for people who don't want to go there,
I'll just read you a מהרש"א Maharsha at the very end on
this אגדתא, aggadeta, such a powerful מהרש"א. Maharsha. And he just points
out this issue about Rabbinic innovation, and he says, I'll just read
you one line, I
know, he says like this. He says, he says like this, he
says, everyone listening, he says, ושלום לאוהבי תורתך דאין זה כי
זה סוף מסכתא veshalom le'ohavei Torasecha de'ein zeh ki zeh sof masechta
seems to be
a פרק perek that we're being עוקר דבר מן התורה, okeir davar
min haTorah, right? Because we're violating all these principles of two עדים
edim and the whole thing and אשת איש. eishes ish. And then
he says, דאין זה עקירה אלא ממידת שלום שלא תעגן האשה וכתיב
דרכיה דרכי נועם שלא תמאס בעיני בעלה ואם תצא לו גט וכולי
לא יונח לצדיק ותשב בביתה ולא תעגן ואמר למען אחי ורעי לפי
שהאמינו עד אחד גם אשה עצמה נאמנת לומר מת בעלי. de-ein zeh
akirah ela mi-middas shalom she-lo ta'agen ha-ishah u-chsiv deracheha darchei no'am she-lo
sima'es be-einei ba'alah ve-im tetzei lo get ve-chulei lo yunach la-tzaddik ve-sishev
be-veisah ve-lo ta'agen ve-amar lema'an achai ve-re'ai lefi she-he'eminu ed echad gam
ishah atzmah ne'emenes lomar meis ba'ali.
Anyway, he says that the point of this is that you might
think this entire פרק perek and these last few פרקים prakim are
all violating the words of the Torah, they're going against the requirement
for עדות. edus. But no, the whole idea of שלום shalom is
part of the way of the Torah, right? דרכיה דרכי נועם וכל
נתיבותיה שלום, Deracheha darchei noam vechol nesivoseha shalom, and it's completely consistent
with the Torah to use that as a lens through which to
interpret and develop הלכה. halacha. Okay, so very beautiful point. We didn't
get to read it fully, but really, really tying in that last
statement with everything we've been seeing in these last פרקים. prakim. יישר
כח Yasher koach to everyone. Especially you.
All right, there's a note here at the end. בנייך, banayich, right?
Yeah, it's an acronym.